The Life Of Muhammadﷺ, The Madinan Period, Volume 2
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki;
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
The people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) sent Sohail Ibn Amr(سهيل إبن عمرو) to negotiate with Rasool Allah ﷺ a truce.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ saw Sohail(سُهيل), he said;
سَهُلَ عَلَيْكُمْ اَمْرُكُمْ
Your matter has become easy.
Because the name Sohail(سُهيل) is derived from Sahula(سَهُلَا), which means easy.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ took it, as a good omen from the name that Tafa'ul(تفاعل) which is called the Tafa'ul(تفاعل)
that peace is on its way, and that Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) are intending on reaching an agreement.
Rasool Allah ﷺ and Sohail Ibn Amr(سهيل إبن عمرو) they deliberated for a while, on the terms of the agreement
and they were very insistent, on not allowing Rasool Allah ﷺ and the Sahabah(صحابه) to enter Makkah that year.
They were very persistent on this particular point
and this is the zeal of Jahilliyah(جاهلية), and the pride of Jahilliyah(جاهلية), the arrogance of Jahilliyah(جاهلية).
They didn't want people to say that he entered it upon us forcefully,
and Rasool Allah ﷺ tried to argue with them, this point to, no avail.
They completely refused.
Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted a settlement, Rasool Allah ﷺ he mentioned before
لَا يَدْعُوْنِيْ اِلاَ خُطَّهْ يَعْظُّمُوْنَ بِهَا
They would not call me, to any plan in which the sanctities are glorified, but I would accept it.
Now, the terms of the agreement were spoken verbally.
So, the only thing left was to write them down.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) was very upset with what he heard.
So, he went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
Aren't you the Messenger of Allah? Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Yes.
Aren't we, the Muslims? He said, Yes.
Aren't they, the disbelievers.? He said: Yes.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said;
فَعَلَامَ نُعْطِي الدَّنِيَّةَ فِيْ دِيْنِنَا اِذَّنْ
Then why should we demean our religion then?
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) saw this as lowering our status and lowering our position.
You are the Messenger of Allah, so you represent Al-Haqq(ألحق).
They are the Mushrikeen(مشركين), they represent evil.
We are the Muslims, who are followers of Haqq(ألحق).
Why should we bargain with them, and why should we reach an agreement with them, to start with?
This was the understanding, the perception of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب).
Rasool Allah ﷺ told Umar(عُمَر);
اَنَا عَبْدُاللهِ وَرَسُولُهْ، لَن أخَالِفَ اَمْرَه’ وَلَنْ يُّضَيِّعَنِيْ
I am the servant of Allah and His Messenger,
I will not disobey Him and He will not abandon me.
Umar(عُمَر) then went to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and said: Isn't he Rasool Ullah? He said: Yes.
Aren't we the Muslims? He said: Yes.
Aren't they, the disbelievers? He said: Yes.
فَعَلَامَ نُعْطِي الدَّنِيَّةَ فِيْ دِيْنِنَا اِذَّنْ
Then why should we demean our religion.
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said;
اِلْزَمْ غَرْزَةْ
Follow him,
أَنَه، رَسُوْلُ الله
He is the messenger of Allah and Allahعَزّوجَلّ will not forsake him.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) later on, would regret, these arguments of his.
Even though, they were, they were made with good intention.
But Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) was very sensitive, when it comes to Haqq(ألحق),
that's why, he is  called Al-Farooq(ألفاروق).
He distinguishes between right and evil.
And he always submits his desires and his intention is to Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
He does not allow himself to follow, the whims of the Nafs(نفس).
He was a very strong believer, Mo'min Al-Qawwi(مؤمن القوي).
So, he would control himself and he only argued here
because of his intentions to give Nusra(نصرة), victory to the religion of Allah.
However, when he saw that the matter, is a matter of revelation
that Rasool Allah ﷺ has instructions from Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
He realized his mistake and he said, he would later on, remember this and say;
So I have gone on fasting, giving alms, praying and freeing slaves,
because of what I did that day, and out of fear for what I said, that day.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says:
إِنَّ الْحَسَنَاتِ يُذْهِبْنَ السَّيِّئَاتِ
The Good deeds erases bad deeds.
So, if you commit a mistake, if you make a sin.
Do a lot of good deeds, after it, in order to erase that sin.
See Umar(عُمَر) here is saying;
I was doing fasting, giving Sadaqah(صدقه), praying voluntary prayer,
and freeing slaves and this is one of the greatest deeds to free slaves.
He was doing it to erase that sin.
So, this is what, we should do, because all of us are going to commit sins.
This is our nature.
Therefore, we need to erase those sins with good deeds.
They started writing the terms of the agreement and these terms were;
Both have agreed to complete truce for a period of 10 years,
during which all the people will enjoy peace and security and will not attack one another.
Next, if anyone from the Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) joins Muhammad(محمد) without permission from his guardian or chief,
he shall be returned to Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
Next, if anyone from the camp of Muhammad(محمد) joins Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), they are not required to return him.
See here, if somebody comes from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), he is returned
but if somebody comes from Muhammad(محمد) he is not returned.
This was one of the conditions that were displeasing to the Muslims.
Both sides agree that they harbor good intentions towards each other.
Next, no theft or treachery shall be condoned.
Next, whoever wishes to enter into an alliance with Muhammadﷺ may do so.
And whoever, wants to enter into an alliance with Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) may do so.
And finally, it is further agreed that you Muhammad(محمد) shall return home this year, without entering Makkah.
At the end of one year, we shall evacuated Makkah for you,
so that you may enter it with your followers to stay for three days only.
You shall carry only the armament necessary for a traveler,
namely your swords in their sheaths, you should not carry any other arms.
They wrote that down and it's time to sign the agreement and have witnesses
and suddenly Abu Jandal(أبوجندل) appears.
Abu Jandal(أبوجندل) who is he?
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) he's the son of Sohail(سهيل), who is writing the agreement with Muhammadﷺ.
He fled from Makkah, he was in chains,
he was imprisoned in Makkah because of being a Muslim,
he heard the news that the Muslims are near,
so he made it, walking through the valleys or mountain passes until, he reaches to Al-Hudaybiyya(اَلحُدَيبية).
And finally, he's happy that he's with the Muslim camp.
Sohail Ibn Amr(سُهَيل بن عمرو) see's him and said: This is the first person, who's case I pick up,
you must return him to me.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
اَجِزْهُوْلِيْ
Allow me to have him?
He said: Either this or nothing,
if you refuse to give Abu Jandal(أبوجندل),
I refuse the agreement.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
We still didn't sign it yet.
Sohail(سُهَيل) was persistent and he refused to back down.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said, to Abu Jandal(أبوجندل);
You must be returned.
Abu Jandal(أبوجندل) said;
O Rasool Ullah you send me back to the disbelievers to test me in my religion.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
Abu Jandal(أبوجندل) be patient and endure your situation for Allah's sake.
He will certainly provide for you,
and those who are suffering with you, a way out of your hardship.
We have made a peace agreement with these people, giving them a pledge by Allah
that we will be faithful to the terms of our agreement,
we should not violate our pledges.
Umar رضي الله عنه was walking next to Abu Jandal(أبوجندل), when he was being dragged away
and he was pointing the handle of his sword,
placing it, pushing it, next to Abu Jandal(أبوجندل)
with the intention of allowing Abu Jandal(أبوجندل) to pick up the sword and strike his father.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) says;
فَظنَّ الرَّجُلُ بِاَبِيْ
Abu Jandal(أبوجندل) preserved his father and didn't want to kill him.
فَنَفَذتِ الْقَضِّيَّهْ
And the issue was over.
Because Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) was whispering to Abu Jandal(أبوجندل) and telling him,
these people are disbelievers, they are worthless.
The blood of any one of them, is no more precious than the blood of a dog.
He's inciting him to do something against his father
but Abu Jandal(أبوجندل) did not take any action.
To the Sahabah(صحابه) men who had dignity, men who had honor, men who had their full trust in Allah
for them to see their Muslim brother taking back to the disbelievers, was disastrous.
This incident of Abu Jandal(أبوجندل) was very difficult for the Muslims to swallow.
Now, Rasool Allah ﷺ only did it because he had a promise from Allah.
Because we don't want anybody to argue and say that,
the Muslims could be handed over to the Kuffar(كفار).
This was done because Rasool Allah ﷺ had a promise from Allah.
That Allah will provide them with a way out.
فَإِنَّ اللَّهَ عَزَّ وَجَلَّ جَاعِلٌ لَكَ وَلِمَنْ مَعَكَ مِنَ الْمُسْتَضْعَفِينَ فَرَجًا وَمَخْرَجًا
This was not forecasting by Rasool Allah ﷺ.
This was Wahii(وحي), this is a promise.
Allah will provide you with a way out, Allah will provide you with a solution to your problems,
but it was very difficult on the Muslims.
So, when Rasool Allah ﷺ ordered the Muslims to slaughter their animals and shave their heads.
No one moved!
Yani(يعني) Rasool Allah ﷺ would just point out his order and they would immediately rush to perform it.
But this time, suddenly no one moved,
now some scholars tried to say that, this was not disobedience on part of the Sahabah(صحابه).
They were just delaying a bit, with the hope and expectation that may be
Rasool Allah ﷺ would receive a revelation that would change the situation,
and maybe there's still a glimpse of hope,
that we might be able to go into Makkah
because there were so eager to make Tawaf(طواف).
They came with that intention, now they're going back empty handed.
So, they said maybe, if we wait a bit the situation could change.
Rasool Allah ﷺ went back and was very angry, upset.
And he told Ummo Salamah(اُمّ سلمة);
The Muslims are ruining themselves, I have given them an order and they have disobeyed.
Ummo Salamah(اُمّ سلمة), the wise, Umm-Ul-Momineen(اُمّ الْمُؤمنين) she said;
Messenger of Allah, Do not talk to them about it, they have been under great pressure
because of all the trouble you have taken to achieve this peace settlement.
And because they now realize that they have to take the long way home without achieving their purpose.
And then she told him: If you want them to follow your order go out and do it in front of them.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ called upon his barber, to cut his hair
and then he would slaughter his animals and his camels
and then all of the Sahabah(صحابه) immediately performed the orders of Rasool Allah ﷺ
but they were very, very sad and depressed state.
The Muslims returned, the whole Hudaybiyya(حُدَيبِية) thing took about between two weeks, 20 days.
On the way, there were two questions on the mind of the Muslims;
1) First question was, we were promised that we would make Tawaf(طواف), so what happened.?
Rasool Allah ﷺ told Umar(عُمَر); Did I tell you that you would do it this year.?
Umar(عمر) said: No.
Then Rasool Allah ﷺ told him than you would make the Tawaf(طواف),
and 2) Second issue: How can we return the Muslims to them,
and Rasool Allah ﷺ said: If we return someone to them,
Allah will provide a way out for them.
If somebody from them comes to us and they're Muslim,
we would send them back and Allah will provide them with the way out,
but if somebody leaves from us to them,
then Allah has rid us from him.
Why do we want, such a person to remain with us?
Such a person who has given up his Islam and ran away.
Why would we want them to stay with us?
Now, an exception was made to this rule with Muslim woman.
So, Muslim woman are not to be returned.
And there's an Ayah(آية) that was revealed to clarify that issue.
So, is this Ayah(آية) making Naskh(نسخ) of the contract
or is it something that is not explicit in the contract and the Ayah(آية) clarifies it?
Allah Ho-Alam(الله اعلم),
this Ayah(آية) is in Surah Al-Mumtahina(سورة الممتحنة).
يَا أَيُّهَا الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا إِذَا جَاءَكُمُ الْمُؤْمِنَاتُ مُهَاجِرَاتٍ
إِذَا جَاءَكُمُ الْمُؤْمِنَاتُ مُهَاجِرَاتٍ فَامْتَحِنُوهُنَّ ۖ اللَّهُ أَعْلَمُ بِإِيمَانِهِنَّ ۖ
فَإِنْ عَلِمْتُمُوهُنَّ مُؤْمِنَاتٍ فَلَا تَرْجِعُوهُنَّ إِلَى الْكُفَّارِ ۖ
لَا هُنَّ حِلٌّ لَهُمْ وَلَا هُمْ يَحِلُّونَ لَهُنَّ ۖ
وَآتُوهُمْ مَا أَنْفَقُوا ۚ
وَلَا جُنَاحَ عَلَيْكُمْ أَنْ تَنْكِحُوهُنَّ إِذَا آتَيْتُمُوهُنَّ أُجُورَهُنَّ ۚ
وَلَا تُمْسِكُوا بِعِصَمِ الْكَوَافِرِ وَاسْأَلُوا مَا أَنْفَقْتُمْ وَلْيَسْأَلُوا مَا أَنْفَقُوا ۚ
ذَٰلِكُمْ حُكْمُ اللَّهِ ۖ يَحْكُمُ بَيْنَكُمْ ۚ وَاللَّهُ عَلِيمٌ حَكِيمٌ۝
O you, who believe when there come to you believing women, refugees
examine and test them, Allah knows best as to their faith.
If you are ascertain that they are believers then send them not back to the unbelievers.
They are not lawful wives for the unbelievers nor, are the unbelievers lawful husbands to them
but pay the unbelievers what they have spent on their dour
and there will be no blame on you if you marry them on payments of their dour to them
but told not to the guardianship of unbelieving women,
asked for what you have spent on their dour
and let the unbelievers ask for what they have spent on the dours of women who come over to you,
such is the command of Allah, He judges with justice between you and Allah is full of knowledge and wisdom.
So, now to the story of Abu Baseer(أبوبصير).
After the agreement was done, a man called Abu Baseer(أبوبصير)
who belongs to the tribe of Thaqeef(ثقيف).
Where are the Thaqeef(ثقيف) from?
Thaqeef(ثقيف) are from At-Taef(اَلطَّائِف), but he was an ally of Bannu Zahra(بنوزَهْرَة).
And Bannu Zahra(بنوزَهْرَة), are one of the clans of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) in Makkah.
Abu Baseer(أبوبصير), was a Muslim,
he fled from the Mushrikeen(مشركين) and he came to Al-Madina(المدينه).
Three days later, two men came asking for him, to be returned.
One of these men is from Bannu Aamir Bin Loaee(بنوعامر بن لؤئي).
One of the branches of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
and the other one was a servant called Kausar(كوثر), who came with him to guide him,
And they had a letter, the letter was presented to Rasool Allah ﷺ, Obae Bin Ka'ab رضي الله عنه read the letter
that, we have an agreement between us
and you have to turn this man back to us.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) you have to go back.
Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) said;
O Messenger of Allah, are you going to send me back to the disbelievers to test me in my religion?
Rasool Allah ﷺ told Abu Baseer(أبوبصير);
We have an agreement with these people and it's not appropriate for us to betray.
وَلَا يَصحُّ فِيْ دِيْنِنَا غَدْرْ
Betrayal is not allowed in our religion.
Rasool Allah ﷺ is not doing this for the Kuffar(كفار), he's not doing it to please them,
he is doing it because these are the rules of Islam.
Even though, the issue relates to Kuffar(كفار).
But these are the virtues and these are the rules of Muslims that we do not betray.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling Abu Baseer(أبوبصير).
لَا يَحِّلُّ فِيْ دِيْنِنَا الغَدْرْ، لَا يَصحُّ فِيْ دِيْنِنَا الغَدْرْ
We cannot betray, in our religion, in our religion, this is not allowed.
So, the Muslim is bound by the rules of Allahعَزّوجَلّ in his dealing with Muslims and non Muslims.
We follow the rule of Allah in everything that we do.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ told Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) just like he told Abu Jandal(أبوجندل)
that Allah will find a way out for you.
Allah will provide you with a way out.
So, now Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) left with these two men.
When they reached to a place called Zul-Khulifah(ذُوالْحليفَة).
There is a Masjid(مسجد) there.
It was Zuhar(ظهر) time, so he, Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) went and prayed two Rak'ah(ركعة)
and he had some dates with him.
So, he told the two men, who came to take him, these Mushrikeen(مشركين),
he said: Come and join me.
So, they also brought some bread that they had, and they had a meal together.
This Aamiri(عامري) man, he pulled out his sword,
in one narration it says that, he pulled out his sword and said;
I'm going to use this sort of mine to strike the Aos(أوس) and Khazraj(خزرج) from morning to night.
Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) told him, Is it a good sword?
He said: Yes, it is!. And I have tested it.
Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) said: Do you mind, if I see it.
The moment, the sword was in the hands of Abu Baseer(أبوبصير), the man was dead!
That's in one narration.
And other narration it says; they went to sleep,
so Abu Baseer(أبوبصير), his hands were tied, so he pulled out the sword with his mouth
and then with his mouth holding the sword, he cut the ropes tying his hands,
and then it struck, this Aamiri(عامري) man and kill him.
So, these are the two narrations, that how he killed Aamiri(عامري).
This second man Kausar(كوثر) when he saw that, he just ran away, flying away,
It says in the narration of Al-Waqedie(الواقدي),
that rocks would fly, from beneath his feet, that's how fast it was going.
and he also says that he raised his Thaub(ثوب), his dress so high,
that his private parts were seen.
I mean, the man was so terrified, he's just flying
and he was not running to the direction of Makkah because it's still far away,
he was running towards the direction of Madina
and Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) was not able to catch him.
I mean, Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) was running after this man, trying to kill him but the man is terrified.
So, he runs into the Masjid(مسجد) and Rasool Allah ﷺ said: When he saw him.
لَقَدْ رَءَى هَذَا ذؤرا
This man has seen something that terrified him.
They told him: What's wrong with you?
He said: My companion was killed and this man is going to kill me too,
and he was seeking their help.
So, they told him calm down! Don't worry!
Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) came in, holding the sword in his hand
and he told Rasool Allah ﷺ;
O Rasool Ullah, You have fulfilled your pledge to them,
and you have handed me over to them, you have done your part.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
وَيْحَ أُمَّهُ
And this part is in Al-Bukhari(ألبخاري), it is authentic.
وَيْحَ أُمَّهُ ، مُسَّعِّرُ الْحَرْبِ لَّوْ كَانَ مَعَه’رِجَالْ
Woe to his mother, he will incite war, if he just had men with him.
The meaning of the statement is that Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) has the capability of starting a war,
if he has men with him.
This statement, what Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) understood from it,
is that Rasool Allah ﷺ is going to hand them over again, if he stays.
So, he decided that he should leave, he left.
Al-Waqedie(الواقدي) by the way, says that
Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) brought, the belongings of Al-Aamiri(ألعامري) to Rasool Allah ﷺ
in order to them divide them, according to the rules of Ghaneemah(غنيمه), the spoils of war.
Rasool Allah ﷺ refused to take them and said;
If I take them then, this is violating my agreement.
It is up to you, to do with it, what you want and Rasool Allah ﷺ refused to take it.
So, Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) is the one who took, what belong to Al-Aamiri(ألعامري).
Now, Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) he cannot go back to Makkah,
he just fled from Makkah and he has killed the man from Makkah.
So, what could he do?
He went to the coast alone.
No one with him, and all what he had with him was a handful of dates
and he split up, that small handful of dates
and he ate from it for three days and that was the only food that he had.
Al-Waqedie(ألواقعدي) says that Allah provided for him, on the coast fish that would come to the coast, dead fish
and he would survive by eating from those fish.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), the story of Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) is amazing.
I mean, a man alone, on the coast with no assistance, with no help,
and there is Ya'ani(يعني), they're looking for him, people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) and he is that difficult, fearful situation.
How Allahعَزّوجَلّ provided for him, and gave him a way out, and gave him victory.
Abu Jandal(اَبُوجَندَل) heard about that,
so he fled from Makkah and joined Abu Baseer(أبوبصير)
and then some other believers who were living under the tyrants, fled and they all joined Abu Baseer(أبوبصير).
And this would make Abu Baseer(أبوبصير), the first Muslim to wage a guerrilla style warfare in the history of Islam.
These men started gathering and there is a narration, According to Al-Waqedie(ألواقعدي).
Al-Waqedie(الواقدي) was one of the scholars of Seerah(سيرة),
however his narrations do not stand up to the requirements of the Ulema(علماء) of Hadith(حديث).
But he mentions that Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) lead a letter writing campaign to the Muslims
who were living among the Mushrikeen(مشركين) to join Abu Baseer(أبوبصير).
And he mentioned in the letter that Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
Woe to his mother, he would incite war if he just had men.
So, what Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) meant by this, is that you men should join him and fight.
Now, they started executing special operations against the caravans of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
So, the news of these operations started spread around and now man from Ghaffar(غفار) would join them
and then men from Johaina(جهينة) and from Aslam(اَسْلَم)
and from the different tribes, all of these young man,
who want to join in this fight in this guerrilla warfare were joining with Abu Baseer(أبوبصير).
Until, he had an army of 300 strong,
300 men with Abu Baseer(أبوبصير), and he's leading them in this war against the caravans of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
Whenever, they would hear of a caravan of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), they would attack it,
take everything in it,
and they would execute everyone in the caravan.
Now, the situation became unbearable for Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
and Rasool Allah ﷺ didn't do anything,
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not involved in this at all,
he did not condemn what Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) was doing, he did not tell him to stop,
Rasool Allah ﷺ was responsible for what was happening in Madina,
he was not responsible for what's happening on the coast.
It's not part of his territory.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ did not do anything to stop this
and by the way, when the news reached Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
that Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) has killed the man from Banni Aamir Bin Loae(بني عامر بن لوئي).
Sohail Ibn Amr(سهيل بن عمرو) was very upset because he belongs to his tribe.
So, he put his back on Al-Ka'aba(ألكعبه)
and he said, I'm not gonna move my back until the Diyah(ديعة) the blood money is paid for this man
and Muhammad(محمد) should pay it.
Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) said;
اِنَّ هَذَا لَسَفَاهة
This is insanity!
What does Muhammad(محمد) have to do with this?
Muhammad(محمد) did his part and he refused to allow Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) to stay in Madina and he return them.
Muhammadﷺ did his part, according to the agreement.
So, the Muslims were doing the bare minimum, of what is required from them, in the contract,
but they're not going to pay any blood money,
and Rasool Allah ﷺ is not going to tell Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) to stop, what he's doing?
So, Sohail Bin Amr(سهيل بن عمرو) said: Then Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) should pay his blood money.
Abu Sufiyan(ابو سفيان) said: And why should Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) pay it,
it is Bannu Zuhra(بنوزُهْرَة) who sent him.
So, he said that Bannu Zuhra(بنوزُهْرَة) should pay it.
Al-Akhnas Bin Shuraiq(ألأخنس بن شريق), who was the head of Bannu Zuhra(بنوزُهْرَة) He said;
We're not going to pay anything.
So, the blood money for this man was lost.
And Sohail Bin Amr(سهيل بن عمرو) received nothing.
See how the Qadar(قدر) of Allah was working things in the favor of the Muslims, and in the favor of Abu Baseer(أبوبصير).
The people of Quraish(قريش), they saw it, as a victory for them in those conditions, in the agreement
and they would come to regret them.
So now, the situation was unbearable for Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
their caravans they barely took a break and started to breathe fresh air
and now they're able to do business again, after a few years of war
and now suddenly a new problem comes up and that's the problem of Abu Baseer(أبوبصير).
Because before Abu Baseer(أبوبصير), before Sulh-Hal-Hudaybiyyah(صلح الحديبيه) Rasool Allah ﷺ was threatening their caravans.
I mean, the Battle of Badr(بدر) occurred because Rasool Allah ﷺ attacked the caravan of Abu Sufiyan(ابو سفيان)
and that's what, many of the sarayah(سراية), many of the dispatches, that Rasool Allah ﷺ would send, were
the purpose and objective of striking against the business roots of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
Now, because of the peace agreement Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) finally will be able to do business again
and they have this problem of Abu Baseer(أبوبصير).
So, they send messages to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) see how, they turned into the situation of begging Rasool Allah ﷺ now,
to change those conditions in the agreement.
The conditions which they were insisted on having, included.
Now, they're begging Rasool Ullah and they're asking him
Bisila-Er-Reham(بصلةالرحم), they're saying;
In the name of our relationship, the relationship that we have, we are relatives.
We asked you in the name of the relationship that we have.
That you call these people in.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ send a letter to Abu Baseer(أبوبصير) inviting them to come back to Madina
and asking the men who belong to the other Bedouin tribes around Madina to go back to their people.
The letter arrived to Abu Baseer(أبوبصير),
when he was in his last moments, he was dying
and he died with the letter of Rasool Allah ﷺ on his chest.
Allah did provide for him a way out,
and Abu Jandal(ابوجندل) returned with the other Muslims to Madina
and this is the promise of Rasool Allah ﷺ that he promised them,
that Allah will find a way out for you.
The thing is that, the Muslims need to follow the commands of Allahعَزّوجَلّ
and Allahعَزّوجَلّ will provide a way out for them.
We move on to Surah Al-Fath(سورةالفتح).
This Surah(سورة) was revealed on the way back from Al-Hudaybiyyah(ألحديبيه).
It was revealed in its entirety then,
and when it was revealed, Rasool Allah ﷺ send someone to call Umar(عُمَر).
Umar(عُمَر) when he heard that Rasool Allah ﷺ was calling him,
he was afraid that it might be some Ayaat(آيات) revealed, reprimanding him for, what he did.
فَرَجَعْتُ وَاَنْا اَظُنْ اَنَّه’ نَزِّلَ فِيْهِ شَيْء
He was afraid and then Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
I received Ayaat(آيات), that are better than everything in the world.
نَزَّلَتْ عليَّ الَّيْلَ سُوْرَةْ هِيَّ اَحَبَّ اِلَيَّ مِنَّ الدُّنْيَا وَمَا فِيْهَا، اِنَّ فَتَحْنَالَكَ فَتْحَا مُّبِيْنَا۝
This narration is in Al-Bukhari(ألبخاري), that I mentioned of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب).
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه he asked Rasool Allah ﷺ, he said;
اَوَ فَتْحً هُوَ
Is it opening?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Yes.
In the name of whom my soul is in His hands, it is an opening.
Now, just an explanation of what the meaning of Fath(فتح) is,
and what the meaning of the word Nasr(نصر) is.
Fath(فتح) is opening
and it's used in Arabic, the original meaning is used when something is locked and opened, that is Fath(فتح).
So, when a key is put into a lock, and it unlocks it.
That is called Fath(فتح).
This meaning was borrowed, to also mean when a land is open,
because the land is locked against the army.
And it's now opened because it's not like you just walk into the territory of the enemy,
it's locked, it's locked in front of your face,
and you have to fight to open it.
Therefore, the word Fath(فتح) is used to refer to a victory that involves taking over land.
While Nasr(نصر) could be used to refer to victory in a battle.
So for example, if you're talking the victory of Badr(بدر).
You say;
إِنْتَصَرنَا فِيْ بَدْر,
we were victorious in Badr(بدر).
But you don't say Fatahna Badr(فتحنا بدر) we opened Badr(بدر)
because it was just a battlefield, it wasn't opened.
But you can say Fath-E-Khaybar(فتح الخيبر) or Fath-E-Makkah(فتح مكه).
You can say Fath-E-Makkah(فتح مكه), that Makkah was opened
because there is land that was taken over in the process.
So, this is the differentiating meaning between Fath(فتح) and victory.
So, Fath(فتح) has an additional meaning over victory
and that is taking overland.
So, the question is, how could Al-Hudaybiyyah(ألحديبيه) be a Fath(فتح)
when there was no land taken over?
One of the Mufassireen(مفسرين) says, it was called Fath(فتح)
because it is the event that led to the opening of Makkah.
It was because of Hudaybiyyah(ألحديبيه) that Makkah was opened,
and Ibn Masood(إبن مسعود) said;
You think that the opening is, the opening of Makkah
but we used to believe that the opening was the opening of Hudaybiyyah(ألحديبيه).
Why was it an opening? Az-Zohri(اَلزُهْرِي) says;
لَقَدْ كَانَ الْحُدَيْبِيَهْ اَعْظَمَ الْفُتُوْحْ
Al-Hudaybiyyah(ألحديبيه) was the greatest of openings,
وَذَلِكَ اَنَّ النَّبِيَّ صلى الله عليه وسلم جَآءَ إلَيْهَا فِيْ اَلْفٍ فِيْ اَرْبَعَ مِائة
فَلَمَّا وَقَعَ الصُلْحْ مَشى النَّاسُ بَعْضَهُمْ فِيْ بَعْضْ
وَعَلِموا وَسَمِعُوا عنِ الله فَمَا اَرَادَه اَحَدٌ الاسْلَامِ اِلَّا تَمَكَّنَ مِنْهُ،
فَمَا مَضت تِلْكَ السَنَتَانْ اِلَّا وَالْمُسْلِمُوْنَ قَدْ جَاوَزُوْاِ إلَى مِائة فِيْ عَشْرَةَ اَلْفْ
That is because Rasool Allah ﷺ came to Al-Hudaybiyyah(ألحديبيه), in a force of 1400.
And when the truce was reached, people started mixing with each other.
And they learned and they heard about Allah.
And anyone who wanted to become Muslim, was able to become Muslim,
because there's now no more threat and fear of becoming Muslim.
So, by the time the two years were over,
the Muslims entered into Makkah in an army of 10,000.
So, in two years, see how the Muslims multiplied
13 years in Makkah and then after that, we have six years until Al-Hudaybiyyah(ألحديبيه).
So, a total of 13 and 6, 19 years and the number was 1400.
In just over two years, the number jumped from 1400 to 10,000.
So, this is the blessing of Sulhal-Hudaybiyyah(صلح ألحديبيه)
that it gave the Muslims a chance to practice Da'wah(دعوة)
because it was a time when there was no risk in becoming Muslim.
And Muslims can travel freely now,
there's no fear so Da'wah(دعوة) spread.
While in Makkah, even though, there was no fighting, but the Muslims were persecuted
and that's why the Da'wah(دعوة) had a difficult time in spreading.
Now, the Muslims had the ability to speak with the people
and the people freely could listen to Islam.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
إِنَّا فَتَحْنَا لَكَ فَتْحًا مُبِينًا۝
Verily we have granted you and manifest victory.
لِيَغْفِرَ لَكَ اللَّهُ مَا تَقَدَّمَ مِنْ ذَنْبِكَ وَمَا تَأَخَّرَ
وَيُتِمَّ نِعْمَتَهُ عَلَيْكَ وَيَهْدِيَكَ صِرَاطًا مُسْتَقِيمًا۝
That Allah may forgive you, your faults of the past and those to follow.
So, Allah gave Muhammad(محمد) victory
and this victory will be the moment in which Allah will forgive for Muhammadﷺ all of his sins.
Now, Rasool Allah ﷺ what sins did he commit.?
We need to understand, put this into perspective, the status of the messenger is very high
and therefore, shortcomings that would come from them,
which for us would seem like doing a great, good deed
because of the highest status of Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء),
what is referred to here as sins, it could be things, that are not appropriate for the highest status of Nabuwwah(نبوَّة).
And these are the things, that Allahسبحانه وتعالى will forgive,
we shouldn't understand these to mean literally sins.
I hope that that meaning is clear,
it is different than what we understand to be sins.
لِيَغْفِرَ لَكَ اللَّهُ مَا تَقَدَّمَ مِنْ ذَنْبِكَ وَمَا تَأَخَّرَ وَيُتِمَّ نِعْمَتَهُ عَلَيْكَ
And fulfill His favor on you.
وَيَهْدِيَكَ صِرَاطًا مُسْتَقِيمًا۝
And guide you on the straight path.
Well Rasool Allah ﷺ was already guided
but what is meant here is, that there's going to be more laws of Shariah(شريعة) that are revealed,
and the Ayaat(آيات) will continue being revealed to Muhammadﷺ and that's the guidance.
وَيَنْصُرَكَ اللَّهُ نَصْرًا عَزِيزًا۝
And that Allah may give you, a great victory.
And this great victory is the opening of Makkah.
And what came after that all of the other victories that the Muslims enjoyed after that,
because of the blessing of Sul'hal-Hudaybiyyah(صلح ألحديبيه).
هُوَ الَّذِي أَنْزَلَ السَّكِينَةَ فِي قُلُوبِ الْمُؤْمِنِينَ
أَنْزَلَ السَّكِينَةَ فِي قُلُوبِ الْمُؤْمِنِينَ لِيَزْدَادُوا إِيمَانًا مَعَ إِيمَانِهِمْ ۗ
وَلِلَّهِ جُنُودُ السَّمَوَاتِ وَالْأَرْضِ ۚ وَكَانَ اللَّهُ عَلِيمًا حَكِيمًا۝
It is He will send down tranquility, in the hearts of the believers.
See, the Muslims they came with intention of Umrah(عمرة) and they were returned back
at a particular moment they gave pledge to die.
So, they prepared themselves, mentally to fight.
And then there was no fighting.
And then suddenly now we have to go back without making Umrah(عمرة).
So, there are a lot of changes that are very difficult to bear that went out within that short period.
Because you prepared yourself mentally for something, you want to do it,
you're prepared to do it, and then you are prevented from doing it,
you try to do something else, and then you are prevented from doing that.
That causes the state of insecurity.
This state of insecurity Allahعَزّوجَلّ says that it was replaced with Sakeena(سكينة),
tranquility came down.
This tranquility was the understanding that the Muslims now had in the promise of Allahعَزّوجَلّ
that we are coming back victorious.
That Allahسبحانه وتعالى has opened for us.
And then Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَلِلَّهِ جُنُودُ السَّمَوَاتِ وَالْأَرْضِ ۚ وَكَانَ اللَّهُ عَلِيمًا حَكِيمًا۝
Allah(He) is reminding the believers that
to Allah belong the forces of the heavens and earth.
Soldiers of Allah, angels are soldiers of Allah, that came down on the Battle of Badr(بدر).
Wind is a soldier of Allah that was sent from the enemy in Ghazwa-Tul-Khandaq(غزوةالخندق).
Rain is a soldier of Allah that was sent on the Muslims in Badr(بدر).
You don't know who the soldiers of Allah are!
وَمَا يَعْلَمُوْ جُنٌوْدَ رَبِّكَ اِلَّا هُوْ
Only Allah knows, who His soldiers are.
The Momineen(مؤمنين), when they heard the first Ayaat(آيات) of Surat-Ul-Fath(سورةالفتح)
that are promising Rasool Allah ﷺ, those great promises.
They said that is for you!. What about us?
They were happy for what Allah gave Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and now they want to know what Allah has promised them.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
لِيُدْخِلَ الْمُؤْمِنِينَ وَالْمُؤْمِنَاتِ جَنَّاتٍ تَجْرِي مِنْ تَحْتِهَا الْأَنْهَارُ
تَجْرِي مِنْ تَحْتِهَا الْأَنْهَارُ خَالِدِينَ فِيهَا وَيُكَفِّرَ عَنْهُمْ سَيِّئَاتِهِمْ ۚ
وَكَانَ ذَٰلِكَ عِنْدَ اللَّهِ فَوْزًا عَظِيمًا۝
That He may admit, the men and women who believe,
to gardens beneath which rivers flow, to dwell therein i.e. forever and remove their ills from them.
And that is in the sight of Allah, the highest achievement for men.
Now, the Ayah(آية) here specifies Mo'mineen(مؤمنين) and Mo'minaat(مؤمنات),
even though when Mo'mineen(مؤمنين) was the masculine form of plural is used,
it's usually refers to both men and women but here's specifically women were mentioned
because the actions that occurred in Sul'hal-Hudaybiyyah(صلح ألحديبيه) were actions of men.
It was men that were going to fight because the battles are fought by men,
but because the Muslim women accompanied
and Muslim women are the ones who have Sabr(صبر) when their husbands leave.
And it is because Muslims women are the ones who take care of their families
when the husband is absent, or when he's killed, Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
Allahعَزّوجَلّ is telling the Muslim women that they will receive the highest status along with, the men.
And then Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَيُعَذِّبَ الْمُنَافِقِينَ وَالْمُنَافِقَاتِ
وَالْمُشْرِكِينَ وَالْمُشْرِكَاتِ الظَّانِّينَ بِاللَّهِ ظَنَّ السَّوْءِ ۚ
عَلَيْهِمْ دَائِرَةُ السَّوْءِ ۖ
وَغَضِبَ اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِمْ وَلَعَنَهُمْ وَأَعَدَّ لَهُمْ جَهَنَّمَ ۖ وَسَاءَتْ مَصِيرًا۝
We talked about what Allah has given the believers.
And now here Allah tells us what He has given their enemies.
And that he may punish the hypocrites men and women.
So, also the women here were mentioned
because they are supportive of their men
and the polytheist men and women who imagine, an evil opinion of Allah
on them is round of evil, the wrath of Allah is on them,
He has cursed them and God's hell ready for them.
And evil is it, for a destination.
So, here we see that the women of the Munafiqeen(منافقين) are mentioned
and the women of the Mushrikeen(مشركين) are mentioned too.
Because they are the ones, who keep their secrets.
They are the ones who support them, they are the ones who take care of their families in their absence.
So, they share the burden.
Now,  Allah repeats the Ayah(آية) again.
وَلِلَّهِ جُنُودُ السَّمَاوَاتِ وَالْأَرْضِ ۚ وَكَانَ اللَّهُ عَزِيزًا حَكِيمًا۝
For to Allah belongs the forces of the heavens and the earth
and Allah is exalted and power full of wisdom.
So, this was mentioned with the believers and now it's mentioned with the non believers.
With the believers, Allah has soldiers fighting for them,
and here with the non believers Allah has soldiers fighting against them.
And then Allah says;
إِنَّا أَرْسَلْنَاكَ شَاهِدًا وَمُبَشِّرًا وَنَذِيرًا۝
We have truly sent you, as a witness, as a bringer of glad tidings and, as a Warner.
Here we see three characteristics of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
1) Number one, Shahid(شاهد) witness, and what is the witness?
A witness is someone, who approves or disapproves a claim that is made by someone else.
So, someone goes to court and he makes a claim,
you bring the witness to approve that claim or to disprove it,
and this is the role of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
He will approve the claims of the believers and the non believers
and he will disapprove the claim.
So, he will approve the claims of the believers
and he will disapprove the claims of the non believers.
2) And then the next characteristic is Mubashir(مبشر)
he gives glad tidings to the believers.
3) Wa-Nazeer(ونذير) he delivers, the warnings to the enemies of Allah.
لِتُؤْمِنُوا بِاللَّهِ وَرَسُولِهِ وَتُعَزِّرُوهُ وَتُوَقِّرُوهُ وَتُسَبِّحُوهُ
وَتُسَبِّحُوهُ بُكْرَةً وَأَصِيلًا۝
In order that you, O men may believe in Allah and His messenger
that you may assist and honor Him
and celebrate His praises morning and evening.
And then Allahعَزّوجَلّ talks about Bay'at-Ur-Ridhwan(بيعة الرضوان).
إِنَّ الَّذِينَ يُبَايِعُونَكَ إِنَّمَا يُبَايِعُونَ اللَّهَ يَدُ اللَّهِ فَوْقَ أَيْدِيهِمْ ۚ
فَمَنْ نَكَثَ فَإِنَّمَا يَنْكُثُ عَلَىٰ نَفْسِهِ ۖ
وَمَنْ أَوْفَىٰ بِمَا عَاهَدَ عَلَيْهُ اللَّهَ فَسَيُؤْتِيهِ أَجْرًا عَظِيمًا۝
Verily, those who pledge to you, do no less than pledge to Allah,
The Hand of Allah is over their hands.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله),
Allah is telling the believers that you did not give your pledge to Rasool Ullah but you gave it to Allah
and the hands of Allah is above their hands,
then anyone who violates his oath does so, to the harm of his own soul
and the Mufassireen(مفسرين) say; None of these Sahabah(صحابه) violated his oath.
All of these 1400 to give the pledge to Rasool Allah ﷺ, none of them violated their oath
and anyone who fulfills what he has covenanted with Allah.
Allah will soon grant him a great reward
and that's why the ones who gave the Bay'ah(بيعة) to Rasool Allah ﷺ under the tree hold very high status.
Now, notice here that Yubayioonaka(يبايعونك) is used in the present form,
even though it was a past event and that is to bring this image to us alive,
to show us the importance of what occurred at that moment.
سَيَقُولُ لَكَ الْمُخَلَّفُونَ مِنَ الْأَعْرَابِ شَغَلَتْنَا أَمْوَالُنَا وَأَهْلُونَا فَاسْتَغْفِرْ لَنَا ۚ
يَقُولُونَ بِأَلْسِنَتِهِمْ مَا لَيْسَ فِي قُلُوبِهِمْ
قُلْ فَمَنْ يَمْلِكُ لَكُمْ مِنَ اللَّهِ شَيْئًا إِنْ أَرَادَ بِكُمْ ضَرًّا أَوْ أَرَادَ بِكُمْ نَفْعًا ۚ
بَلْ كَانَ اللَّهُ بِمَا تَعْمَلُونَ خَبِيرًا۝
The desert Arabs, the Aa'raab(أعراب) who lagged behind,
these are the ones who did not come with the believers in Sul'hal-Hudaybiyyah(صلح ألحديبيه).
Why didn't they come?
they felt that Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) are too strong and the Muslims will be killed.
So, they stayed behind.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says the desert Arabs who lagged behind will say to you;
We were engaged in looking after our flocks, and herds, and our families.
So, this the excuse they came forth with,
we stayed behind because of our families and because of our wealth.
Now Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله)
the 1400 who went with Rasool Allah ﷺ, didn't have any wealth or didn't have any families.
So, this is not an acceptable excuse in the eyes of Allah.
The fact, that you have a family does not excuse you from going out Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
The fact, that you have business to take care of and a job to attend to,
does not excuse you from going Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
So, it's an invalid excuse and then Allah says;
Do thou(you) then ask forgiveness for us, they were asking you to select to forgive them.
They say what their tongues, what is not in their hearts,
say who then has any power at all to intervene on your behalf with Allah.
If His will is, to give you some loss or to give you some profit.
But Allah is well acquainted with all that you do.
And Allah says about them;
بَلْ ظَنَنْتُمْ أَنْ لَنْ يَنْقَلِبَ الرَّسُولُ وَالْمُؤْمِنُونَ إِلَىٰ أَهْلِيهِمْ أَبَدًا
وَزُيِّنَ ذَٰلِكَ فِي قُلُوبِكُمْ وَظَنَنْتُمْ ظَنَّ السَّوْءِ وَكُنْتُمْ قَوْمًا بُورًا۝
Nay, you thought that the Messenger of Allah,
Allah is telling us the real reason why is, they stayed behind.
Nay you thought that the Messenger and the believers would never returned to their families.
This seems pleasing in your hearts and you conceived an evil thought,
for you are people lost in wickedness.
وَمَنْ لَمْ يُؤْمِنْ بِاللَّهِ وَرَسُولِهِ فَإِنَّا أَعْتَدْنَا لِلْكَافِرِينَ سَعِيرًا۝
If any believe not in Allah and His messenger,
we have prepared for those who reject Allah a blazing fire.
وَلِلَّهِ مُلْكُ السَّمَاوَاتِ وَالْأَرْضِ ۚ
يَغْفِرُ لِمَنْ يَشَاءُ وَيُعَذِّبُ مَنْ يَشَاءُ ۚ وَكَانَ اللَّهُ غَفُورًا رَحِيمًا۝
To Allah belongs, the dominion of the heavens and the earth.
He forgives whom He wills and He punishes whom He wills
but Allah is oft forgiving, most merciful.
سَيَقُولُ الْمُخَلَّفُونَ إِذَا انْطَلَقْتُمْ إِلَىٰ مَغَانِمَ لِتَأْخُذُوهَا ذَرُونَا نَتَّبِعْكُمْ ۖ
يُرِيدُونَ أَنْ يُبَدِّلُوا كَلَامَ اللَّهِ
قُلْ لَنْ تَتَّبِعُونَا كَذَٰلِكُمْ قَالَ اللَّهُ مِنْ قَبْلُ ۖ
فَسَيَقُولُونَ بَلْ تَحْسُدُونَنَا ۚ
بَلْ كَانُوا لَا يَفْقَهُونَ إِلَّا قَلِيلًا۝
Those who lagged behind will say;
when you are free to march and take booty in war, permit us to follow you.
Now Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله),
they refused to join Rasool Allah ﷺ in Hudaybiyya(حديبية)
because they thought that Rasool Allah ﷺ and the Sahabah(صحابه) will be defeated.
They saw that things were contrary to their belief.
Now, Allah has promised the believers Ghaneemah(غنيمه), spoils of war.
So, these Aa'raab(أعراب) want to join.
For Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) they're willing to join.
When it's for Allah, they don't want to join.
As a punishment for them.
They were prevented from going out with the Muslims in Khaybar(خيبر),
as a punishment for them.
When they were told not to join in Khaybar(خيبر),
they said: You are jealous.
You want to take the spoils for yourself,
يُرِيدُونَ أَنْ يُبَدِّلُوا كَلَامَ اللَّهِ ۚ
So, Allah says those who lagged behind will say;
When you are free to march and take booty in war, permit us to follow you.
They wish to change the Allah's decree.
Say; Not thus Will you follow us?
Allah has already declared this beforehand.
Then they will say but you are jealous of us.
Nay, but little do they understand such things.
These are people who don't have understanding.
They don't have Fiqh(فقه), their understanding is limited to Duniya(دنيا).
They measure things in dollar sign, that's how they see things.
Everything for them is worldly, they're attached to Duniyah(دنيا),
their hearts are not attached to Allah and not attached to Aakhirah(آخرة).
They do not think about the unseen, they do not think about the future what happens to us after death.
They are limited to the understanding of this Duniyah(دنيا).
A secular way of thinking.
And then Allahعَزّوجَلّ telling them;
You see they will be punished from attending Khaybar(خيبر) only but after that they can join.
So, now Allah says;
قُلْ لِلْمُخَلَّفِينَ مِنَ الْأَعْرَابِ سَتُدْعَوْنَ إِلَىٰ قَوْمٍ أُولِي بَأْسٍ شَدِيدٍ تُقَاتِلُونَهُمْ أَوْ يُسْلِمُونَ ۖ
فَإِنْ تُطِيعُوا يُؤْتِكُمُ اللَّهُ أَجْرًا حَسَنًا ۖ
وَإِنْ تَتَوَلَّوْا كَمَا تَوَلَّيْتُمْ مِنْ قَبْلُ يُعَذِّبْكُمْ عَذَابًا أَلِيمًا۝
Say to the desert Arabs, who lagged behind,
you shall be summoned to fight against the people given to wamind war.
أُوْلِي بأسٍ شَدِيْدٍ
they're very tough, in fighting
then shall you fight, or they shall submit?
Then if you show obedience Allah will grant you a goodly reward.
But if you turn back as you did before,
He will punish you with a grievous penalty.
This tough enemy that Allah told them that they will meet.
Some say; It is talking about the Murtaddeen(مرتدين) who followed Musailima Kadhaab(مسيلمه كذاب)
and some say its talking about the Persians and the Romans, Allah-Ho-Alam(الله اعلم).
لَيْسَ عَلَى الْأَعْمَىٰ حَرَجٌ وَلَا عَلَى الْأَعْرَجِ حَرَجٌ وَلَا عَلَى الْمَرِيضِ حَرَجٌ ۗ
وَمَنْ يُطِعِ اللَّهَ وَرَسُولَهُ يُدْخِلْهُ جَنَّاتٍ تَجْرِي مِنْ تَحْتِهَا الْأَنْهَارُ ۖ
وَمَنْ يَتَوَلَّ يُعَذِّبْهُ عَذَابًا أَلِيمًا۝
No blame is there on the blind,
nor is there blame on the lame, nor on one ill, if he joins not in war.
These are excused from fighting in Jihad(جهاد).
But he that obeys Allah and His Messenger, Allah will admit him to gardens beneath which rivers flow
and he who turns back Allah will punish him, with a grievous penalty.
And Allah says again the ones, who pledged allegiance under the tree.
لَقَدْ رَضِيَ اللَّهُ عَنِ الْمُؤْمِنِينَ إِذْ يُبَايِعُونَكَ تَحْتَ الشَّجَرَةِ
فَعَلِمَ مَا فِي قُلُوبِهِمْ فَأَنْزَلَ السَّكِينَةَ عَلَيْهِمْ وَأَثَابَهُمْ فَتْحًا قَرِيبًا۝
Allah's good pleasure and that's why this Bay'ah(بيعة) is called the Bay'ah(بيعة) of pleasure, Ar-Ridhwaan(ألرضوان).
Allah's good pleasure was on the believers
when they swore fealty to the under the tree,
He knew what was in their hearts and He sent down tranquility to them
and the rewarded them with a speedy victory.
This tree was a tree that was known after that
and some Muslims would come and pray next to that tree
because of the special occasion that occurred there on the streets mentioned the Quran.
So Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه ordered that, that tree be cut down
because Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) was worried that this could lead to Shirk(شرك),
it could end up being like Zaat Anwaat(ذات أنواط),
which existed in the time of Jahilliyah(جاهلية).
The people of Jahilliyah(جاهلية) used to think that this tree Zaat Anwaat(ذات أنواط) would give them Barakah(بركة).
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) ordered this tree to be cut down.
Even though, it's a special tree Rasool Allah ﷺ sat under it,
and the tree is mentioned in Qur'an
but in Islam, it substance not symbols that count.
وَمَغَانِمَ كَثِيرَةً يَأْخُذُونَهَا ۗ وَكَانَ اللَّهُ عَزِيزًا حَكِيمًا۝
And many gains will they acquire, besides
and Allah is Exalted in Power full of wisdom.
So, Allah promised the believers, bounties.
The first of them was Khaybar(خيبر) and then many other gains will be acquire.
And this is talking about the Ghanaem(غنائم) that the Muslims will win over, until the day of Judgment.
وَعَدَكُمُ اللَّهُ مَغَانِمَ كَثِيرَةً تَأْخُذُونَهَا فَعَجَّلَ لَكُمْ هَٰذِهِ وَكَفَّ أَيْدِيَ النَّاسِ عَنْكُمْ
وَكَفَّ أَيْدِيَ النَّاسِ عَنْكُمْ وَلِتَكُونَ آيَةً لِلْمُؤْمِنِينَ وَيَهْدِيَكُمْ صِرَاطًا مُسْتَقِيمًا۝
Allah has promised you many gains that you shall acquire
and He has given you these before hand and He has restrained the hands of men from you,
that it may be a sign for the believers
and that He may guide you to a straight path.
وَأُخْرَىٰ لَمْ تَقْدِرُوا عَلَيْهَا قَدْ أَحَاطَ اللَّهُ بِهَا ۚ
وَكَانَ اللَّهُ عَلَىٰ كُلِّ شَيْءٍ قَدِيرًا۝
And other gains there are, which are not within your power
but which Allah has compassed.
And Allah has power over all things.
وَلَوْ قَاتَلَكُمُ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا لَوَلَّوُا الْأَدْبَارَ ثُمَّ لَا يَجِدُونَ وَلِيًّا وَلَا نَصِيرًا۝
And if the unbelievers should fight you
they would certainly turn their backs,
then they would neither find protector nor help.
So, if the disbelievers are going to retreat.
Why didn't the Muslims fight them?
Because Allay says that if they would have fought you they would have been defeated.
سُنَّةَ اللَّهِ الَّتِي قَدْ خَلَتْ مِنْ قَبْلُ ۖ وَلَنْ تَجِدَ لِسُنَّةِ اللَّهِ تَبْدِيلًا۝
Such has been the practice approved by Allah already in the past
no change will you find to the practice approved by Allah.
So, it's a law of Allah,
that the believers will win,
they might lose in a battle but eventually, they win.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَالْعَاقِبَةُ لِّلْمُتَّقِيْنْ
See it's a law of nature just like we have laws of physics and laws of chemistry.
This is a law, believers will win.
They might lose a battle, but they win the war.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
إِنْ تَنْصُرُوا اللَّهَ يَنْصُرْكُمْ
Allahعَزّوجَلّ will give victory to those who gives support to Allah.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَالْعَاقِبَةُ لِّلْمُتَّقِيْنْ
The end belongs to the ones who have Taqwa(تقوى).
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
يَا أَيُّهَا الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا إِنْ تَنْصُرُوا اللَّهَ يَنْصُرْكُمْ وَيُثَبِّتْ أَقْدَامَكُمْ
Allahعَزّوجَلّ will make your feet firm.
So, the Muslims Yes, they lost in Uhud(أحَد)
but eventually, they won the war against Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
The Muslims might have lost some battles against the Romans,
but eventually they have won,
they might have lost in some battles with the Persians.
But eventually they conquered the entire domain of the Persian Empire.
So, this is a promise from Allahعَزّوجَلّ as long as they are fulfilling
the commands of Allah, and as long as they're believers,
and as long as they are giving Nusrah(نصرة) to the religion of Allah.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ has promised them with victory.
If this is the case, that the enemy would flee,
why didn't they fight them.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَهُوَ الَّذِي كَفَّ أَيْدِيَهُمْ عَنْكُمْ وَأَيْدِيَكُمْ عَنْهُمْ بِبَطْنِ مَكَّةَ مِنْ بَعْدِ
مِنْ بَعْدِ أَنْ أَظْفَرَكُمْ عَلَيْهِمْ ۚ وَكَانَ اللَّهُ بِمَا تَعْمَلُونَ بَصِيرًا۝
And It is He! Who has restrained their hands from you,
and your hands from them in the midst of Makkah
after that He gave you the victory over them and Allah see's well all that you do.
We talked about this incident when Kuffar(كفار) sent forty men
in order to take prisoners from the Muslims.
They ended up falling as prisoners in the hands of the Muslims.
And the Rasool Allah ﷺ released them.
So, here Allah is telling us that Allah prevented war.
It was prevented by the Muslims, discovering these kuffar(كفار)
beforehand and that prevented the Kuffar(كفار) from taking prisoners
because if they took prisoners, then war would have occurred
and then Allahعَزّوجَلّ stopped the war by Rasool Allah ﷺ freeing the 40 men from the Kuffar(كفار)
because if he didn't, then that could have possibly lead to war.
So, why is all of this, why was war prevented ?
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
هُمُ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا وَصَدُّوكُمْ عَنِ الْمَسْجِدِ الْحَرَامِ وَالْهَدْيَ مَعْكُوفًا أَنْ يَبْلُغَ مَحِلَّهُ ۚ
وَلَوْلَا رِجَالٌ مُؤْمِنُونَ وَنِسَاءٌ مُؤْمِنَاتٌ لَمْ تَعْلَمُوهُمْ أَنْ تَطَئُوهُمْ فَتُصِيبَكُمْ مِنْهُمْ مَعَرَّةٌ بِغَيْرِ عِلْمٍ ۖ
لِيُدْخِلَ اللَّهُ فِي رَحْمَتِهِ مَنْ يَشَاءُ ۚ
لَوْ تَزَيَّلُوا لَعَذَّبْنَا الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا مِنْهُمْ عَذَابًا أَلِيمًا۝
They are the ones, who denied revelation and hindered you from the sacred mosque
and the sacrificial animals.
Detained from reaching their place of sacrifice.
See here, had there not been believing men and believing women,
whom you did not know that you were trampling down
and on whose account, a crime would have accrued to you,
without your knowledge, Allah would have allowed you to force your way
but he held back your hands.
It's because there were some Mo'mineen(مؤمنين) in Makkah
Allahعَزّوجَلّ prevented war from happening.
To save those Mo'mineen(مؤمنين) because of the Muslims made their way through Makkah by force,
there would have been bloodshed and some Muslim men and Muslim women would have been killed
and that is why the Qadar(قدر) of Allah was to hold back the Muslims and the Kuffar(كفار) from war.
And also Allahعَزّوجَلّ, had a plan for the people of Makkah.
Allah says that He may admit to mercy whom He will.
Many of the people have Makkah were admitted into the mercy of Allahعَزّوجَلّ and they became Muslim.
If the believers would have been apart from the non believers.
We should certainly have punished the unbelievers among them with the grievous punishment.
So, this was the Qadar(قدر) of Allah(الله) that prevented war.
It was not the command of Allah to the Muslims.
This is not Amr Shar'ie(أمر شرعي), it's not a command from Allah to the Muslims not to fight
but it was Amr Qadri(أمر قدري) it was a decree of Allah to the Muslims not to fight.
إِذْ جَعَلَ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا فِي قُلُوبِهِمُ الْحَمِيَّةَ حَمِيَّةَ الْجَاهِلِيَّةِ
فَأَنْزَلَ اللَّهُ سَكِينَتَهُ عَلَىٰ رَسُولِهِ وَعَلَى الْمُؤْمِنِينَ
وَأَلْزَمَهُمْ كَلِمَةَ التَّقْوَىٰ وَكَانُوا أَحَقَّ بِهَا وَأَهْلَهَا ۚ
وَكَانَ اللَّهُ بِكُلِّ شَيْءٍ عَلِيمًا۝
While the unbelievers got up, in their hearts the heat and kant of ignorance, Jahilliyah(جاهلية).
Allah sent down His tranquility to His Messenger, and to the believers
and made them stick close to the command of self restraint,
and well were they entitled with, and worthy of it
and Allah has full knowledge of all things.
If the believers would have acted in haste,
then these things that Allahعَزّوجَلّ mentions, Lima'arah(لِمَعَرَّةْ) could have happened.
But they were restrained and they were patient and this was good for them in the long term.
لَقَدْ صَدَقَ اللَّهُ رَسُولَهُ الرُّؤْيَا بِالْحَقِّ ۖ
لَتَدْخُلُنَّ الْمَسْجِدَ الْحَرَامَ إِنْ شَاءَ اللَّهُ آمِنِينَ
آمِنِينَ مُحَلِّقِينَ رُءُوسَكُمْ وَمُقَصِّرِينَ لَا تَخَافُونَ ۖ
فَعَلِمَ مَا لَمْ تَعْلَمُوا فَجَعَلَ مِنْ دُونِ ذَٰلِكَ فَتْحًا قَرِيبًا۝
Certainly, Allah has showed to His Messenger, the vision in truth.
You will surely enter Al-Masjid-Al-Haram(ألمسجدالحرام) if Allah wills, in safety.
You remember that we talked about the vision that Rasool Allah ﷺ saw that he's making Tawaf(طواف) in Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
So, Allah is saying that that will happen,
however it didn't happen at that particular time but it will happen in the future and it did.
You will surely enter Al-Masjid-Al-Haram(ألمسجدالحرام), if Allah wills in safety,
with your heads shaved, hair shortened and not fearing anyone
and Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) when they did make Hajj(حَجْ) with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
They were not fearing anyone
when that happened in Hajjah-Tul-Wida'a(حجة الوداع), the farewell Hajj(حَجْ).
He knew, what you did not know and has arranged for that a conquest near at hand.
And then Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
هُوَ الَّذِي أَرْسَلَ رَسُولَهُ بِالْهُدَىٰ وَدِينِ الْحَقِّ لِيُظْهِرَهُ عَلَى الدِّينِ كُلِّهِ ۚ
وَكَفَىٰ بِاللَّهِ شَهِيدًا۝
It is He, Who send His messenger with guidance and the religion of truth to manifest it, over all religion
and sufficient is Allah as witness.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ tells us that the religion of Allahعَزّوجَلّ that was sent through Muhammadﷺ
and the guidance that was sent with Muhammadﷺ, will manifest over all religion
and then the last Ayah(آية),
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says and this is in Ayah(آية) that is continuous virtues for the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم, Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
مُحَمَّدٌ رَسُولُ اللَّهِ ۚ
وَالَّذِينَ مَعَهُ أَشِدَّاءُ عَلَى الْكُفَّارِ رُحَمَاءُ بَيْنَهُمْ ۖ
Muhammad(محمد) is the Messenger of Allah,
and those who are with him are forceful against the disbelievers, merciful among themselves.
Remember, we said that the disbelievers refused to write down Muhammad(محمد) Rasool(رَسول) Allah(الله),
that he is the Messenger of Allah,
they refused to testify and witnessed that he is the Messenger of Allah.
So, Allah revealed it, in Qur'an
that Allah has sent Muhammadﷺ as a Messenger and Muhammad(محمد) is Rasool Ullah(رسول الله)
and here we have characteristics of the Sahabah(صحابه).
Number one, they are forceful against the disbelievers,
رُحَمَاءُ بَيْنَهُمْ ۖ
and they are merciful among themselves.
Unfortunately, we find that, there are some Muslims who are the total opposite of this description.
So, they are forceful against the believers and they are very merciful towards the disbelievers.
تَرَاهُمْ رُكَّعًا سُجَّدًا يَبْتَغُونَ فَضْلًا مِنَ اللَّهِ وَرِضْوَانًا ۖ
You see them bowing and prostrating in prayer seeking bounty from Allah and His pleasure.
So, one of the most prominent characteristics is their Salah(صلاة).
You find them, you look at them, you will see that, they are in Sujood(سجود) or they are in Rakooh(ركوع),
سِيمَاهُمْ فِي وُجُوهِهِمْ مِنْ أَثَرِ السُّجُودِ ۚ
Their mark is on their faces from the trace of prostrations.
So, prostration leaves a trace on the face, it's not talking about the dark mark that is on the forehead
it's talking about the light that shines from the face because of Sujood(سجود).
ذَٰلِكَ مَثَلُهُمْ فِي التَّوْرَاةِ ۚ
That is their description in the Taurah(توراة).
وَمَثَلُهُمْ فِي الْإِنْجِيلِ كَزَرْعٍ أَخْرَجَ شَطْأَهُ فَآزَرَهُ فَاسْتَغْلَظَ
فَآزَرَهُ فَاسْتَغْلَظَ فَاسْتَوَىٰ عَلَىٰ سُوقِهِ يُعْجِبُ الزُّرَّاعَ لِيَغِيظَ بِهِمُ الْكُفَّارَ ۗ
وَعَدَ اللَّهُ الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا وَعَمِلُوا الصَّالِحَاتِ مِنْهُمْ مَغْفِرَةً وَأَجْرًا عَظِيمًا۝
And their description in the Gospel is, as a plant which produces its offshoots and strengthens them.
So, they grow firm and stand upon their stocks the lighting the sowers,
so that He(Allah) may enrage by it, them, the disbelievers.
Allah has promised those, who believe and do righteous deeds among them forgiveness and a great reward.
So, the analogy or the similitude of the believers in the Gospel is
like a plant that grows until, it is firm and it is unbreakable and that angers the disbelievers.
These are the Ayaat(آيات) of Surat-Ul-fath(سورةالفتح) that were revealed
after this great opening of Sul'ha Hudaybiyyah(صلح الحديبية).
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًا
اَلسَّلَامُ عَلَيْكُمْ وَرَحْمةُ الله وَبَرَكَاتُه’